各位親愛的弟兄姊妹,主內平安
Dear all brothers and sisters, shalom
讓我先祝賀錦宣家三十九歲生日快樂
May I first send my greetings and wishes to
Farewell Park Alliance Church for this 39th anniversary
Happy birthday
今日我們選擇的經文是
大家好熟悉《史道行傳》一章開始的記載
Today we are going to look at the book of Acts chapter 1
The beginning of this book
你說我都識背了,還有什麼好說的?
Or maybe you would say I know this verse as well, what to talk about?
我連耶路撒冷、猶太傳、地撒瑪利亞直到地極都背得準確
I can memorize the verse in Jerusalem, in all Judea, Samaria, and to the ends of the earth
好,你不要看聖經,回答我下面這個問題
Ok, now, please do not refer to the Bible and answer me this question
耶穌在一章八節講聖靈是第幾次講到聖靈?
When Jesus talked about the Holy Spirit in verse 8
How many times did He talk about this?
從第一節開始,耶穌講了多少次聖靈?
Ever since verse 1, how many times did He mention about the Holy Spirit?
不知道啊,who cares?
I don't know, who cares?
要知的
You have to know
你看看聖經
Refer to the Scriptures
耶穌在第二節提到聖靈
藉著聖靈來吩咐使徒
In verse 2, He said
After giving instructions through the Holy Spirit to the Apostle He had chosen
這是教導我們三一真神彼此的關係
This is about the relationship between the triune God
第五節,第二次講到聖靈
In verse 5, this is the second time that the Holy Spirit is mentioned
這裡講聖靈的洗
It mentions baptized with the Holy Spirit
就是講《舍行傳》第二章發生的事情
This is about chapter 2 in the book of Acts
所以我們不要隨便想像什麼叫做聖靈的施洗
Please do not just think about what is baptized with the Holy Spirit by your own mind
其實來到第八節
這就是第三次講聖靈降臨
And in verse 8, it should be the third time
that the Scripture mentions about the Holy Spirit
不要用check room來投票
唯有不用你舉手
你告訴我這樣的答案對不對?
Do you think this answer is correct?
不對
No, it's not
因為你漏了最重要的那次
Because you have missed out the most important time
沒有啦,我看到是三次講聖靈的
Well, I did not see the fourth time
第六節
Verse 6
他們聚集的時候
Then they gathered around him
為什麼他們要聚集呢?
Why do they have to gather?
第四節說
耶穌和使徒聚集的時候
Verse 4 said
When Jesus gathered with the apostles
耶穌祝福他們說
Jesus gave them this command
不要離開耶路撒冷
Do not leave Jerusalem
要等候父所應許的
But wait for the gift my Father promised
等什麼?
What to wait for
等誰?
Who to wait for
誰是父所應許的
Who is the Father promised
聖靈
The gift, the Holy Spirit
所以這段經文最重要的那句講聖靈
是故意不講的
That's why the most important part
that talks about the Holy Spirit
it was not mentioned
英文我們叫做loud silence
有沒有聽過?
In English, it's called loud silence
不講就是最重要那句
If you don't talk about it
it is the most important
因為這是耶穌的祝福
Because this is Jesus' command
這是他們聚集的原因
This is the reason why they gathered
這是父神所應許
This is what the Father promised
這也是主耶穌曾經跟使徒說過的
他們聽過的
And this is what Jesus had told the apostles about
所以我們的印象就是
耶穌叫他們來就送他們去
So we always have this impression
that Jesus comes and sends the disciples
馬太福音、馬學福音是這樣說的
In the book of Matthew and Mark, it said so
你又會背了
I know you can memorize that
所以你們要去
Therefore you go
使萬民作我的門徒
Make disciples
你們往普天下去
傳福音給萬民聽
Go to the world and preach the gospels
我們沒有時間了
We don't have enough time
曾牧師給我三十分鐘
還要扣上全譯
Pastor John gave me a limited time
你回去看《路加福音》二十四章
You can refer to the book of Luke, chapter 24
四十六節到五十二節
很長的
Verse 46 to 52
It's a long passage
耶穌祝福他們
不要離開耶路撒冷
Jesus gave them the command
Do not leave Jerusalem
要等候父所應許的
But wait for the gift my father promised
你衝了出去
就留了最重要的東西
If you just go with your own will
and you left the gift behind
所以不要這麼快
Don't rush
去之前
Before you go
要等候
There's a wait
等誰?
Who to wait to?
不是等法叔
是等候聖靈
It's waiting for the Holy Spirit
這些不能翻譯的
對不起
但是《史道行傳》比《路加福音》更詳細
The book of Acts
describing these in more details
因為他們聚集的時候
耶穌祝福他們等候聖靈
Jesus gave his command to them
that they have to wait for the Holy Spirit
到主耶穌最後一次提聖靈降臨這句說話
When Jesus mentioned
the Holy Spirit descending to them
其實前面還有一個連接詞
conjunction
In fact, there is a conjunction
before everything he said
那個不是一個普通的
and or but
這麼簡單的連接詞
It is not just a conjunction
like and or but
希臘文alaa
這個是一個很強調的連接詞
In Hebrew, it says alaa
但聖靈降臨
But the Holy Spirit descends
可能英文要說however
In English, we may say however
加重語氣
emphasize it, however
前面說什麼
What was before that
為什麼後面要加個但字開始
Why did the word however was mentioned in the scriptures
因為我從來讀聖經都不讀這些
You may say, oh, I don't know
I never realized
我讀聖經就是問有什麼教訓
我衝出去做
I believe the scriptures tell me what to do
and I just go and do it
先聽清楚耶穌說什麼
Please listen carefully to what Jesus said
第一,他叫我們等候聖靈
First, to wait for the Holy Spirit
第二,他提到聖靈之前
他有個連接詞說
但聖靈降臨
before waiting for the Holy Spirit
there is a conjunction, but
上半句耶穌是在回答使徒的問題
In the first part, he was answering the apostles' questions
上半節和下半節
哪半節重要些
What Jesus said is more important
the upper verse or the lower verse
當然是下半節聖靈降臨
You may say, oh, of course
those things that he said later
你明不明白我們的問題出在哪裡
Do you know the problem
我們讀聖經很霸道
When we read the scriptures, we are very
耶穌明明說了上下兩半
我們截了上一半
我們只說下一半最重要
Jesus mentioned two things
and we just pick one only
行不行呢
Do you think that's okay?
耶穌回答使徒什麼問題呢
What did Jesus answer to the disciples?
主啊,我讀的是和合本
祢復興以色列國
就在這時候嗎
Lord, are you at this time
going to restore the kingdom to Israel?
復興
Restoration
你說這個是很屬靈的
我們要教會復興
We would like the church to be restored
三十九年的歷史
前面的三十九年
我們祈求復興
感謝讚美主
We have 39 years of history
and we look forward to this restoration
對不起
這裡不是在說復興教會
I'm sorry
This is not about restoration of the church
我們一見到復興兩個字
就跳進了我們的結論裡
不可以的
When we look at the word "restore"
we just conclude the verse is about restoration
and it's not correct
復興誰
Who to be restored
復興以色列
Restore Israel?
不是
復興以色列國
Restore the kingdom of Israel
懂得聽這句話嗎
Do you understand this verse?
在羅馬帝國統治之下
Under the Roman Empire
試圖問這個問題要很小心
When the apostles ask this question
they have to be extra careful
沒有23條有國安法
We don't have a law 23
but we have national security law
明白《使徒行傳》第一章嗎
Do you understand this?
明白了
醒了
Do you understand?
試圖問的是一個政治的問題
What the apostles were asking
were the political questions
耶穌如何回答這個政治的問題呢
How did Jesus answer this political question?
上半重要還是下半重要呢
Is the upper part more important or the lower part more important?
看你什麼顏色
Depends on your colour
不是這樣讀聖經的
No, it's not the way we read the scriptures
耶穌的答案
Jesus' answer
我們真的要小心聽
We have to listen carefully
因為他的答案其實是背著舊約聖經的金句
Because his answer refers to the Old Testament
如果我們不懂的話
我們很容易誤會了耶穌的意思
If we don't fully understand
we might misunderstand Jesus' teaching
起初神創造天地
你知道我背著創世紀一章一節
In the beginning
God created the heaven and the earth
That was in Genesis 1:1
耶和華是我的目者
你知道我背著四篇二十三篇
The Lord is my shepherd from Psalm 23
You all know that
我的神
為什麼離棄我
My God, why do you abandon me?
你知道耶穌背著哪一章聖經嗎
Do you know which verse Jesus refers to?
啊!耶穌好痛苦在十字架上大叫救命啊
錯了
Oh, Jesus, when he was crucified on the cross
He was in such pain that he screamed
耶穌不是痛苦叫救命啊
No, Jesus is not screaming because of the pain
我只看到你的眼睛
我看不到你的樣子
戴了口罩
不過我看到你好像不知道我在說什麼
From where I stand, I can see your eyes
And I guess you are wondering what I'm talking about
耶穌是背著四篇二十二篇第一節
Jesus was referring to Psalm 22, verse 1
四篇二十二篇全篇所說的主題
正正就是上帝從來都沒有離開過
In Psalm 22, the passage was about
God has never left us
環境看來,我們會問上帝往哪裡去了?
When we look around, we may ask where did God go?
但是Cp 22篇正正就是說不要看周圍
But Psalm 22 teaches us not to look around our surroundings
所以你不知道耶穌背著這句
你就解錯了他的意思
If you do not know that Jesus was referring to the Old Testament
you might have got the wrong meaning
拿著雞毛當靈箭
You have another idea
不可以的
No, that's not right
請問耶穌在這裡背著哪一節金句?
Which verse is Jesus referring to?
以塞俠書49章第6節
It is from Isaiah 49, verse 6
沒有印出來給大家
I did not print it out for you guys
你有iPhone請你點擊以塞俠書49章第6節
If you have your phone
please turn to Isaiah 49, verse 6
我讀給大家聽
Let me read it for you
「現在他說:你作我的僕人,使雅各眾之派復興,使以色列中德保存的歸回尚為小事。」
He said, "It is too small a thing for you to be my servant
to restore the tribes of Jacob
and bring back those of Israel I have kept."
「我還要使你作外邦人的光,叫你施行我的救恩,直到地極。」
「I will also make you a light for the Gentiles,
that you may bring my salvation to the ends of the earth.」
看到耶穌引用的這句金句嗎?
Now you see which verse does Jesus refer to?
那你才明白什麼叫做「直到地極」
Then only then you understand what does it mean by the ends of the earth.
《使徒行傳》28章保羅去到地極了嗎?
In the book of Acts 28, does Paul reach the ends of the earth?
你一定是另投說「未」
I am sure you will say no.
都未去到南極、北極
It never reached Antarctica and the Arctic.
那裡只有北極熊和企鵝
No, there is only polar bears and penguins.
那你起碼要來中國、印度、四大文明古國
At least you have to come to China.
不是
《以賽亞書》49章第6節很清楚說
It is clearly said in this verse
「地極」和「外邦」是平衡的同義詞
The meaning of the ends of the earth and the Gentiles are parallel in meaning.
所以《路加福音》24章如果你回去真的看一看
你就會發覺那裡不是說地極
那裡是說「萬邦」
If you look at Luke 24
It was not talking about the ends of the earth
but it is about all nations.
保羅去到地極了
Paul reached the ends of the earth.
因為條條大道通羅馬
Because all routes go through Rome.
羅馬就是外邦世界的中心
Rome is the center of the Gentiles' world.
所以《使徒行傳》28章停在羅馬是地極
Therefore when the book of Acts stops at Rome
it is the end of the world, it is the end of the earth.
你需要舊約《以賽亞書》去明白《使徒行傳》
You need Isaiah to understand the book of Acts.
你更加明白《使徒》問復興以色列國的問題
So now you understand why the apostle asked the question
about restoration of the kingdom to Israel.
其實《以賽亞書》已經回答了
In fact, the book of Isaiah answers this question.
在舊約這個復興
當然是講亡國被老回歸重建的歷史
Of course, we talk about restoration in the Old Testament
is about the decline of a nation and...
Coming back to Jerusalem?
Coming back to Jerusalem.
現在使徒已經在耶路撒冷了
And now the apostles are already in Jerusalem.
現在是羅馬帝國統治著他們
It's under the Roman Empire's rule.
所以甚麼叫做復興以色列國?
So what does it mean by restore the kingdom to Israel?
是憤慮黨西門的政綱
憤慮黨是甚麼人?
The Salads.
他們不是法利賽人
They are not Pharisees.
他們不是薩都該人
They are not...
Satruses.
再加多一句
他們不是愛悉尼、死海古卷的Ascenes
They are not Ascenes.
他們是Salads, 憤慮黨的西門
They are the Simon of Salads.
耶穌揀選了一個憤慮黨人做他的使徒
Jesus chose a Salad to be his apostle.
教會的領袖
The leader of the church.
你說耶穌,你好揀唔揀?
你乜揀個勇武攬炒?
Jesus, why do you choose this Salad to be your church leader?
耶穌成晚祈禱
Jesus prayed all night.
《路加福音》第六章
In Luke, chapter 6.
不單止揀了憤慮黨人西門
Not only Simon of the Salad.
他亦都揀了瑞利、馬太,有冇印象?
And also he chose the tax collector, Matthew.
唔考我哋嘅翻譯
喺古老嘅英文聖經嗰度翻譯
瑞利唔係譯做tax collector
係譯做republicans
In the scriptures, it is translated as republicans
instead of tax collectors.
然後馬太後日投票俾Trump
What do you say if Matthew vote for Trump?
Republic of Rome
羅馬共和國
馬太係支持帝國
Matthew support the republic
所以佢先至做瑞利呢個行業
And that's why he become the republican.
所以你明白去到耶穌臨升天之前
啲使徒喺度拗乜嘢
So you know before Jesus ascend to heaven,
you know what the apostles were arguing.
佢哋唔係拗緊教會復興
They were not arguing for the restoration.
佢哋唔係拗緊耶穌幾時返嚟
Not about when Jesus coming back.
佢哋拗緊
憤慮黨同republican之間嘅政治立場
They are arguing for the political views
between the zealots and the republicans.
呢個喂
講嘅一班人
點傳福音呀
You may think all such group of people
how can they spread the gospel.
少郎主唔使寫落去啦
So we don't have to move on to the book of Acts.
第二章就撕裂
Chapter 2 was some fights between one another.
第三章就撕了
Chapter 3 is about...
你寫落去囉
我哋識寫架嗰個歷史係咪咁樣
Do you think the history should be written like this?
聖經其實好現實嘅
Actually the scriptures is very related.
只要你肯讀
Only if you are willing to read them.
唔係瞇埋眼就背一章第八節
Not just close your eyes and memorize the verse.
係耶穌講嘅
This is what Jesus said.
係聖經嘅記載嚟㗎
This is written in Exodus.
請問福音如何由耶路撒冷傳到猶太傳地和撒瑪利亞
How can the gospel go from Jerusalem to Judea and Samaria
and to the ends of the earth?
使徒開猜傳會議
The apostles held meetings.
十二個使徒
一半出去猜傳
一半留返喺樹木養
Among twelve apostles, half go out and spread the gospel
and half remains in the church.
真係值得再讀一次使徒行傳
It's really worthy for us to read the books of Exodus.
你睜開咗隻眼已經
Now we open our eyes.
使徒行傳第八章第一節
In the book of Acts, chapter 8, verse 1.
你有冇iPhone呀?
我唔係問你有冇聖經呀
Whether you have the Bible app in your phone.
從這日起
耶路撒冷的教會大遭逼迫
除了使徒以外
門徒都分散在猶太和撒瑪利亞
On that day a great persecution broke out
against the church at Jerusalem
and all except the apostles were scattered
throughout Judea and Samaria.
第四節
Verse 4
有iPhone嘅同學一齊讀
Please read with us.
那些分散的人往各處去傳道
Those who had been scattered
preached the word wherever they went.
睇到嗎?
Do you see?
聽見嗎?
Do you hear?
嗰啲去咗倫敦 去咗溫哥華 去咗悉尼
去咗Toronto嘅人做乜嘢呀?
Those who go to different cities around the world.
哦 佢哋去退休
What did they do?
哦 佢哋去避難
Retirement?
哦 佢哋同香港say 永別
They are saying goodbye to Hong Kong forever?
No.
佢哋出去傳道
They are going to preach the word of God.
聖靈都唔使同教會討論 商量 表決
It is not required for the Holy Spirit to discuss with the church.
唔係過半數先至做㗎
Doesn't get the vote and the Holy Spirit get to decide.
一個唔該 逼北嚟到
And where the prosecution comes?
目的
And the purpose?
福音傳到地極
There is only one purpose for this.
It is to have the gospel to be sent to the end of the earth.
請問福音點樣從亞洲去到歐洲㗎?
Do you know how does the gospel goes from Asia to Europe?
哦 馬其頓嘅呼聲
Because of the Macedonian vision.
夜晚黑堡羅見到異象有馬其頓人話請過來幫助我門
At night Paul sees the vision that Macedonian called for help.
咁佢哋就過去歐洲囉
And so they go to Europe.
你再讀返前面一啲
If you refer to the back of front in the book of Acts.
保羅出去第二次傳到頭頭碰著黑
When Paul started preaching, he faces a lot of difficulties.
耶穌的靈不許 聖靈又禁止
有冇讀過呀?
The spirit of Jesus and the Holy Spirit
do not allow him to move forward.
保羅點解一個人出去咁淪盡呢?
You may say why Paul face such big difficulties?
係啦 因為佢冇同埋佢師父巴拿巴一起去
That's because he did not go with his mentor, Banabas.
點解佢冇同巴拿巴一起去?
Why didn't he go with Banabas?
《士徒行傳》十五章記載
二人起了爭論 甚至彼此分開
In the book of Acts, chapter 15,
it mentions both of them argued and divided.
對唔住呀 陳牧師同曾牧師坐喺前面
借你哋做個例 得唔得?
May I use Reverend Zhang and Reverend Chan as an example?
曾牧師好緊張 摸下陳牧師個額
Reverend Zhang is very nervous.
《士徒行傳》兩人起了爭論 甚至彼此分開
弟兄姊妹點算?
When the apostles start the argument and even divided between themselves,
what do you say?
安提柯教會冇分裂
The church of Antioch did not divide.
安提柯冇開始有間聖巴拿巴堂 冇間聖保羅堂
The church of Antioch did not start. The church of Banaba.
安提柯教會double 咗佢嘅mission budget
The mission budget in the church of Antioch was increased.
巴拿巴同馬可去居比路傳福音
Banaba and another person went to...
Cyprus?
Cyprus spread the gospel together.
保羅和西拉就聖靈又禁止 耶穌的靈又不許
原來是趕他們過去歐洲
When you see that the spirit of Jesus does not allow them to do so,
it forces them to go to another place.
嗌交唔好㗎 啱
It's not good to argue, that's correct.
撕裂唔得㗎 要和好 啱
Divide between one and another is not good. Better reconcile.
不過聖靈嘅工作出乎意料之外
But the work of the spirit is full of surprises.
請問福音係點樣帶到去羅馬㗎?
Do you know how did the gospel reach Rome?
保羅係點樣去羅馬㗎?
How did Paul go to Rome?
佢第三次傳道結束
During his third preaching mission.
佢趕返耶路撒冷首五巡節
He returns to Jerusalem for the Pentecost.
返到去之後
教會領袖約保羅來述職
After he reached Jerusalem,
the church leaders asked Paul to come.
邊個係耶路撒冷教會領袖呀?
Who is the leader of the church of Jerusalem?
瓦國 耶穌嘅弟弟
Jacob, Jesus' brother.
James.
就係瓦國書嗰個瓦國
James, from the book of James.
就係寫你哋唔係因信清義
係因行為清義嘅嗰個瓦國
James, the one who wrote about
you are not justified by faith, but justified by work.
而家瓦國同保羅見面啦
Now, James is meeting with Paul.
保羅同瓦國講
「愛邦人信主」
點樣 點樣 點樣 感謝讚美神
Now, Paul said to James,
the Gentiles hear the gospel
and it was amazing and everything.
瓦國話俾保羅聽
「輕台」
James said to Paul,
「Big brother」
你知道喺耶路撒冷
信奉者道嘅猶太人
成千上萬
並且熱心法律
Do you know that the people in Judea
follow the words of God
and they follow the law?
並且佢哋話你保羅
唔守摩西嘅律法
And they said, you Paul,
you did not follow the laws of Moses.
唔俾下一代守國禮
You do not allow the next generation
to have circumcision.
咁點算呀?
What to do?
嗱 不如咁啦
How about this?
唔係我作嘅
係少林寺記載嘅
I didn't make this all up.
It was written in the scriptures.
二十章
記唔記得呀?
Chapter 20.
我哋冇時間讀啦
Do you remember?
But we don't have time to go through that.
雅各同保羅講
你不如上聖殿去還願
俾人睇下你係
循規蹈矩嘅一個人
James said to Paul,
how about you go to the temple
and show people that you follow the laws?
呢四個字
你係保羅
你冚唔冚得落呀?
Imagine you are Paul.
Can you take that?
保羅妥協
Paul agrees.
Compromised.
忘記初衷
He forgot his first calling.
保羅願意咁樣做
Paul is willing to do so.
結果聖殿暴動
And there was a disruption in the temple.
唔止呀
七個人無罪釋放嗰隻呢
And release of the seven persons.
係咪?
跟住就上訴該殺
And they make their appeal to Kaiser.
所以保羅係坐住business class
去羅馬公堂送佢去
And therefore Paul is sitting on the first class of the plane to go to Rome.
但聖靈降臨
But the Holy Spirit descends.
你要等候聖靈嘅工作
You have to wait for the work of the Holy Spirit.
完全唔係我哋嘅計劃嚟㗎
It's completely not what we think about.
唔係教會生生性性㗎
It's not about the church behaving according to the laws and the teachings.
係睇環境真係皺哂眉頭㗎
If you look at the surroundings, you get the frustrations.
又逼白又撕裂又爭吵又神學不同
乜嘢都齊晒
There were persecution, divisions, arguments and differences in theology and thinking.
但福音就係咁樣直到地極
And that is how the gospel goes to the ends of the world.
同頭一天開始
It was started from the beginning of...
直到今天2020年11月1日香港感受宣導會
Until today, November 1st of 2020 at this church.
我哋聽到神嘅道
We hear God's word.
如果係長老會嘅傳統
我哋應該一齊回應
Thanks be to God.
If it is in the perspiration traditions, we should all say, "Thanks be to God."
感謝主
Thank you, God.
多謝我哋嘅翻譯
Thank you for your message.
多謝您收睇時局新聞,再會!